I was the chief of CIA counterterrorism
operations in Pakistan in the immediate
aftermath of 9/11. When I returned to
CIA headquarters in May of 2002, I was
asked if I wanted to be trained in what
they called the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques. I had never
heard that term before. I didn't know
what it meant. And the way it was
explained to me in my mind was clearly
torture. And I was well read enough to
know that we have the Federal Torture
Act of 1946. We have the United Nations
Convention Against to Torture. We have
other laws that very clearly delineate
what we are allowed to do in national
security custodial interrogations. I
declined the training. I I was the only
one of the 14 people who were approached
who declined to be involved. It was 100%
crystal clear to me that there were a
lot of people inside the CIA who were
opposed to the torture program. People
were writing cables back to headquarters
from the secret site saying, "Whoa, this
is not what I I signed up for. I'm not
going to do this. I want to come home."
That's called a curtailment where you
curtail your overseas assignment. It's a
careerending decision to just say, "Send
me home. I'm not doing this." There were
people who resigned from the secret
site. There were nurses who fainted
while watching the torture sessions.
There were doctors from the Office of
Medical Services who would write, "Wait
a minute. Wait a minute. I took an oath
to do no harm and you want me to be
there to revive this guy after you kill
him so that you can torture him more?
I'm not doing that. And then finally in
2007, I said something to ABC News. My
only regret was that I
left five and a half years on the